[Music]
Stanford University all right I want to
discuss again we did do the ideal gas
did we not the ideal gas of point
particles now I want to talk about the
ideal gas of particles which are not
point particles under what circumstances
is a gas well approximated by an ideal
gas an ideal gas is one where particles
don't collide with each other and the
answer is when the density of the gas is
low enough and it doesn't matter very
much if the particles themselves have
some size and some structure as long as
the distance between particles is much
much larger than the structure of the
particle itself it's still an ideal gas
so particles in this apart achoms
molecules and so forth molecules
certainly have structure they can rotate
they can vibrate but this leads to a
very big paradox in classical
statistical mechanics and there's one
that was only resolved by quantum
mechanics it was considered one of the
big paradoxes about classical about the
statistical mechanics at the end of the
nineteenth century and as I said it only
got resolved
by the same ideas that resolved the
problem that essentially almost exactly
the same ideas which resolved the big
problem about blackbody radiation which
we will come to so if you don't know
what the problem of blackbody radiation
is don't worry about it right now the
problem of molecules had a very very
similar
flavor to it let me tell you what the
problem molecules is and we'll do it by
doing an example a molecule with
structure now this is a very very
simplified version of the structure of a
molecule but it's enough to see what the
problem is let's replace the point
molecule oh darn it let's replace the
point molecule by a pair of atoms which
are connected by a rigid rod now in the
notes that are on the internet are which
are available to you I did the problem
explicitly of a molecule built like this
which is free to rotate around in three
dimensions I'm going to simplify it here
because all of the essence of it is in a
simpler story namely the molecule is
only free to rotate in a plane all right
so the molecule is free to rotate around
an axis and the axis could be one of the
atoms a simple example would be that
there's a heavy atom and a light atom
the heavier atom will tend not not to
move around so much and the light atom
will revolve around it at the end of
this entirely rigid rod the atom has in
addition to the usual kinetic energy of
motion overall motion it has an
additional energy of rotation and that
additional energy of rotation can be
excited for example by collisions
between two such molecules two such
molecules come
gather and they hit each other
off-center and even if they weren't
rotating after they hit each other they
will start rotating so the rotational
energy is part of the energy and has to
be accounted for in studying the
statistical mechanics and the energetics
of this gas of these molecules okay
so let's first consider the energy of
rotation and as I said for simplicity
this is purely for simplicity let's take
one of the atoms to be heavy enough that
it moves with a much lower velocity than
the other one really of course the
complex system rotates about its center
of mass but if one of the atoms is heavy
then the center of mass is close to that
atom it's like a solar system the solar
system revolves around the Sun well not
quite the earth doesn't quite revolve
around the Sun the Sun and the earth
revolve around the point which is the
center of mass of the Sun of the earth
as assuming we didn't have to worry
about Jupiter but it's not such a bad
approximation to put the Sun at the
center and say the earth moves around it
and in that case you can ignore the
motion of the the central one the heavy
one and the kinetic energy involved is
just a kinetic energy of the light one
moving around ok this is not essential
this is in no way essential to the story
ok so what is the energy of such a
molecule well first of all there's a
translational degree of freedom of a
molecule that just means the motion of
the center of mass and its energy is
exactly what you would expect it's the
total momentum squared divided by twice
the total mass of the molecule I'll use
capital m to indicate the total mass of
the composite molecule and that's one of
the terms of the energy and this of
course a term like that for each
molecule so it was really a summation
sign which I won't bother writing out
and then there's the rotational energy
so for the rotational energy let's just
imagine the center of mass
is one of these molecules and the other
one gets to move in a circle it gets to
move in a circle and let's take the
radius of the molecule to be small R
okay so what is the kinetic energy let's
take the light atom and make its mass
little m and of course the kinetic
energy of rotation is nothing but the
kinetic energy of moving around in the
circle
it's just M times the angular velocity
angular velocity but the tangential
velocity let's call it V squared divided
by two this is not the overall velocity
this is the component of the velocity ah
if we pretended that the center of mass
was standing still so it's the velocity
around the circular velocity and that's
it that's the kinetic energy let me
rewrite that the velocity moving around
in the circle is proportional to the
angular velocity so let's call the
angular velocity theta dot the time
derivative of the angle the angular
orientation of a molecule theta dot
times what are 30 dot times R and we can
plug this in here and this gives us M R
squared + R now is not a dynamical
variable it's the fixed length of the
rigid rod connecting the two atoms
that's of course associated with the
rigidity of certain molecular bonds
sometimes molecular bonds are pretty
rigid and this would be an instance in
which their molecular bond was very very
rigid and didn't allow much inward
outward motion I so via so so this
becomes M R squared over 2 times theta
dot squared now mr squared divide M R
squared is just a constant and has a
name it's the moment of inertia
so we can give it a name and it's
usually called I I / 2 times theta dot
squared and for our purposes the
definition of the moment of inertia is
nothing but mr squared it's just a
symbol that I use to simplify the
formula I over 2 times theta dot squared
now theta dot or theta excuse me is a
generalized coordinate if we go back to
our studies of mechanics we remember
that we can think of any possible
description of the coordinates of a of a
system as being more or less on an equal
footing and work either with position
along here or we can work with angle and
apply the standard rules of classical
mechanics the standard rules of
classical mechanics involve among other
things constructing a Hamiltonian which
constructing momenta which are conjugate
for the coordinates the coordinate in
this case is Theta and the momentum
conjugate to it is called angular
momentum all right what is the rule
incidentally this is the kinetic energy
it's also the Lagrangian for those who
like lagrangians this happens to be the
Lagrangian of the circular motion so
think of it that way what is the
definition of the momentum conjugate to
theta anybody remember the definition of
conjugate momentum the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to the time
derivative of the coordinate all right
so that just means the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to theta dot so
the angular momentum now now I had a
reason for not writing that this is
equal to L the Lagrangian because the
standard symbol for angular momentum is
also L sorry about that
I will the L that I'm writing here is
not the Lagrangian it is the angular
momentum standard symbol and it's equal
to the derivative of this object with
respect to theta dot just as well you
know the story I don't have to tell you
silver so the angular momentum is just I
theta dot now again this is not
Lagrangian oh I suppose I could write
this as script DL for Lagrangian this is
angular momentum and it's I times theta
dot
let's now rewrite the kinetic energy in
terms of angular momentum instead of
theta dot here we have it in terms of
theta dot easy enough we just solve for
theta dot in terms of I and L and plug
it back in what do we get for the
kinetic energy we get the extra term in
the kinetic energy is l squared over
twice the moment of inertia when we
square theta dot we get l squared over I
squared well as an I in the numerator
here I squared in the denominator we get
1 over I so l squared over I and this
becomes now the energy of a molecule in
terms of its linear momentum that's this
there are three components of it just as
there would be for a point particle and
one additional momentum namely the
angular momentum this is the expression
for the energy
the new thing now though from the point
of your statistical mechanics is that a
configuration involves the position the
overall center of mass position the
momentum and also the angular momentum
of and also the angular coordinates okay
here is a rule and I think you probably
discovered this player by yourself but
by now that whenever the energy consists
of two terms that are independent of
each other with no interaction between
them and here there's no interaction
between the rotational motion and the
translational motion there's nothing for
example in this expression which links
these two terms together rotation can
happen independently of translational
motion nothing to link them together
when you have a situation where there
are two completely independent to go
degrees of freedom the partition
function factorizes in other words let's
let's first write out the partition
function for a single particle let's put
a single molecule in all right at a
certain temperature then the partition
function for that single molecule is sum
or the integral sum of all the
configurations and I won't write that
yet but let's write e to the minus beta
and now we have the usual let's try the
P squared over twice the mass that's it
right yep and then plus l squared over
2i but let's just write that as a
product e to the minus beta l squared
over 2i we have to sum this over all the
configurations of the particle that
means first of all integrating over the
center of mass location of the atom
that's exactly the usual D cubed X we
have to integrate over the momentum of
the linear momentum of the part
that's the usual D cubed P but now there
are new coordinates that we have to
integrate over namely the position of
the molecule along the circle and its
angular momentum just as we integrate it
over position and momentum here we have
to integrate over angular position and
angular momentum so we might as well
write down another integral here D theta
D L and that's it that's the partition
function for a single particle what
would the partition function be for n
particles well it would be a multiple
integral of a similar kind but we've
already learned from experience that
when you have n particles it's just the
nth power of the partition function for
one particle so later on we can remember
that we should take the nth power of
this capital n where n is the number of
particles this is the central thing that
we have to be able to compute okay first
of all the integral over the position
that's as always the volume to the nth
power let's throw in our friend the one
over N factorial which I forgot to put
into this formula here and I don't have
enough room anymore yeah we can put in 1
over N factorial usual one over N
factorial for identity of particles ok
volume to the nth comes or volume
yeah we're only doing it for one
particle so let's just do it for one
particle volume period we'll come back
to the multiple volume from DP of D
cubed X now remember what we got by
integrating e to the minus beta P
squared over 2m d cubed P trying to
remember I think for each moment it's
the square root of two M PI over beta to
the third power
and the three comes from the three
dimensions of space okay so it's 2m PI
over beta to the three halves power okay
so we have that but now we have another
factor coming from here the other fact
that coming from here looks exactly like
Oh what about first of all the theta
integration what does the theta
integration give to pi it's sort of like
the volume except the volume is just two
pi the volume of the theta variable is
just two pi so if I really want to keep
track of all the numerical constants
there's a factor of two pi and then I
get to erase the D theta all right and
then there is the integral DL now the
integral of VL is the same kind of
integral that we did here again it's a
Gaussian integral easy to do instead of
being to the third power since there's
only one angle not three angles there's
only one angle ah there's just a single
integration to do here but but it's the
same kind of integration the only
difference is instead of where you see
em you now have I so the next factor
would be square root of 2i pi provided
by beta and that's it one more factor
another way of saying it is there were
three directions of space plus an extra
internal direction and so the third
power of one over beta got replaced by
the fourth power of one over beta one
extra power of one over beta the extra
volume coming from the integration over
the position of the circle that's just a
numerical factor of two pi this is the
partition function for a single diatomic
molecule of a particularly simple kind
okay now notice I have restricted the
molecule to move in a plane a real
molecule can
/ round in all three dimensions and it
gets a little more complicated but I
wanted to do the simplest example in the
notes is the example where the rigid
molecule can move around in three
dimensions alright so this would be the
simplest diatomic molecule and that's
that's and we will raise that to the nth
power and divide by n factorial for a
gas of n particles okay do this is the
only know thing is this let suppose box
around it the dive very simple diatomic
the simplest possible diatomic molecule
Oh exactly the equations I needed I
think if we've seen these before at some
point in our in the history of our
studies
yes and Newtonian limit yes geodesic
glare question a Newtonian limit that's
what that's what's going on here okay
so let's rewrite it now let's not
rewrite it let's take us logarithm the
main thing that we're interested in
usually is the logarithm of the
partition function logarithm of the
partition function is as always
proportional to in well let's let's be a
little bit let's let's actually just do
it n minus n log n factorial coming from
the in factorial and denominator volume
to the end so I plus law plus n log
volume plus n log of the volume you can
combine these together so that it
involves the logarithm of the density I
showed you how to do that using
Sterling's approximation but I'm not
going to bother even doing it we've done
that before you would do exactly the
same thing here and then you get plus
plus or minus minus three-halves
logarithm of beta there's also the
logarithm through the three-halves the
logarithm of 2 m pi e I'll include that
at the end over here but let's not worry
about it for the moment and now there is
oh sorry you get incorrectly is 3 n log
beta 3 over 2 n log beta but now from
the beta dependence in the last turn
layer let's write it explicitly minus
another n log beta and then a whole
bunch of constants logarithm of 2 M PI
logarithm of 2 I PI all those constants
logarithm of 2 pi
I all the various constants let's just
add them up here and call it constant a
numerical addition to the to the log of
the partition function which will not
contribute to anything interesting you
know the first term should be just log
in that for ya are good thank you yeah
- loggin factorio factor to the second
to last term which one in LOC theta
here next one in log beta of n over 2
log beta ok so it's simple it's just one
extra coordinate add it to the 3
coordinates but I want to keep them
separate because just to show that they
come from different places all right now
what is the energy per molecule the
energy per molecule is just a derivative
of log Z with respect to beta with a
minus sign alright that will give us
minus or with when the minus sign is
accounted for it will give us 3n over 2
times 1 over beta differentiate log beta
you get 1 over beta but that's just a
temperature so let's just call it
temperature 3n over 2 and that's the
classic formula for the point particle
gas but now there's another term plus
1/2 n times the temperature so the whole
upshot is that the energy per particle
is 2 n T rather than 3 halves
and T or is this just more energy there
for a given temperature there's more
energy there because the rotational
degrees of freedom get excited okay so
that's what this is here now there's a
puzzle and the puzzle goes as follows
imagine that you now tuck the limit in
which the radius of the molecule got
smaller and smaller and smaller
shouldn't you'll eventually get closer
and closer to the point particle limit
after all is it really reasonable that
you can tell imagine that this rod which
connects one point particle we're
thinking about a model now of two point
particles connected by a rod
and now imagine shrinking the rod until
the two point particles are 10 to the
minus 10 plunk distances apart in other
words until the distance between the
points is infinitesimally smaller than
any any distance scale that we ever
think about in physics shouldn't it
become the point particle if it does it
means that you should only have three
halves nt energy in the system but
somehow this doesn't go away it doesn't
depend on the radio Oh incidentally
we're in this formula up there is the
radius of the molecule embedded it's an
eye and that adds to this constant here
but the constant doesn't get
differentiated to calculate the average
energy so no matter how small you make
this molecule no matter how tight you
make that molecular bond this term does
not go away well this gets a little bit
crazy now arm do we have to worry
separately about the electrons rotating
no even an atom is not a point particle
an atom might contain 20 electrons going
around it do we have to include 20
additional contributions like this
coming from the 20 electrons going
around it and perhaps the electrons
themselves secretly have some Oh the
nucleus of course has many constituents
and so forth so even a simple atom is
not a point particle it contains many
many degrees of freedom if you were to
do the classical calculation you will
find out that there is a 1/2 in T for
each internal degree of freedom of the
atom this doesn't make a lot of sense
this should be no way that you could
tell from the properties of a gas at a
low temperature certainly at a very very
high temperature where the molecules may
collide so hard that they would knock
each other into smithery
and so forth you could tell that the
molecules were not pointing particles
but at very very low temperatures where
the velocities are very small momenta
are small how can it possibly be and the
gas is very dilute particles are far
from each other how can it possibly be
that the thermodynamics the energy of
the system in particular remembers that
the the atoms are composite shouldn't be
the case the solution to this puzzle and
we'll do it now the solution to this
puzzle is quantum mechanics so I thought
I would just work out the quantum
mechanical formula I'll show you how
that comes about I'm not sure how it
comes about was going to pretty much
assume a formula and show you what
actually does happen for a real molecule
how the paradox gets resolved or all we
have to know the only thing we have to
know about quantum mechanics is that
angular momentum is quantized that
angular momentum does is not a
continuous variable it's a variable
which comes in discrete multiples of a
basic unit and that basic unit is
Planck's constant all right so let's go
back let's go back to this formula over
here I think we don't need this anymore
let's go back to the energy to the
rotational energy e equals L squared
over 2i and now write that the possible
values of the angular momenta are not a
continuous variable but that L is
quantized in units of let's call it n
times H bar plunks constant times H bar
l is equal to n times H bar H bar of
course being a very small number so that
means the steps between different values
of the angular momentum are very small
but nevertheless it's not continuous and
then we can write the energy not as l
squared over 2i which is correct but as
N squared H bar squared over 2 hi do I
have that right I think I have that
right and what is the variable now which
distinguishes one state from another n
and n and incidentally n can be any
integer positive or negative why
positive or negative well negative
angular momentum corresponds to rotating
in one direction positive angular
momentum in the other direction angular
momentum zero just means not rotating at
all this is the energy of the molecule
quantum mechanically
and that's all that we need from quantum
mechanics that we replace the sum over
States by the sum over in and that's it
so let's let's write down now what the
partition function is for the quantized
angular momentum incidentally there is
no real change associated with the first
term the P squared over 2m quantum
mechanic auto mechanics to really do it
correctly but it gives the same answer
it's the l squared over 2i which is most
sensitive because of the quantization of
angular momentum momentum itself linear
momentum is not quantized as a rule at
least in a very big similar system it's
the angular momentum which is quantized
ok so now let's write down the partition
function again for a single molecule and
Z now becomes equal to the sum over n of
e to the minus beta times the energy
which is N squared H bar squared over
twice the moment of inertia
that's it the some of it in here is too
hard to do there's no simple closed-form
for something over in all right so we
can't do it but we can do enough we can
do some approximations which will give
which will show us exactly what's going
on
[Music]
sometimes approximations are more
illuminating than than an exact formula
first of all there are two regimes of
temperature which behave quite
differently over which are extreme
situations very high temperatures very
low temperatures let's examine the two
cases of very high temperatures and very
low temperatures very high temperatures
means beta very small so keep that in
mind
high temperatures T is 1 over beta I
always get myself confused and I always
naturally first think when temperatures
are high that means large beta but then
I have to correct myself and say no when
temperatures are high beta is small when
temperatures are low beta is high so
keep that in mind ok what happens what
should we do first let's do first high
temperatures high temperatures means
beta is small and let's take this
quantity here and imagine plotting it
let's see how plotted over here
horizontal axis is in n is an integer
and what I'm plotting is the thing in
this exponential here it has a value at
each integer now when beta is very small
forget for the moment the quantization
let's just look at this as a function of
n when beta is very small temperature is
very high this is a very slowly varying
exponential when beta is very small it's
a very slowly varying exponential
and to a high approximation under the
circumstance the sum over the values of
in each each Delta in here Delta N
equals one so each one of these is
separated by one unit of n the height is
the function and so the contribution of
each one of these strips here is
basically just the area of it and so
forth so a high approximation as long as
this is smooth and gentle enough which
means the temperature high enough this
sum can be replaced by the integral over
n the integral over n replaced by the
integral over n and if we do replace it
by the integral we're back to the
classical calculation instead of
integrating over angular momentum we're
integrating over in but that doesn't
make any difference and is proportional
to the angular momentum is the same
integral except for a numerical constant
and we don't care about numerical
constants very much so the first thing
is that at very high temperatures it
simply reproduces the same answer as the
classical calculation at least for
everything interesting the sum can be
replaced by the integral because the
function is extremely smooth and slowly
varying on the other hand all right so
that's one fact high temperatures
classical answer and what was the
classical answer not three-halves kt not
three-halves t for the energy per
molecule but twice T or I'm not too over
T twice T in other words the rotational
energy is excited just as it would be in
the classical case on the other hand
let's go to low temperatures and low
temperatures beta is very big
that means this function is a very
rapidly falling function and in fact if
beta is big enough if the temperature is
small enough the function varies
enormous ly before it even gets to N
equals 1 and then between N equals 1 and
N equals 2 it falls even further and so
forth to approximate such a rapidly
varying and rapidly falling function by
the integral is nonsense that's not a
good thing to do not approximately given
by the integral in fact the smart way to
do the calculation is just to recognize
that each succeeding term is very much
smaller than the previous one and just
approximated by the sum of a small
number of terms in particular just
approximated by the first two terms in
via in the sum here why the first two
terms well let's just take the first
term to begin with what's the first term
the first term corresponds to N equals
zero remember we have to sum over all
positive negative and zero values of n
are positive and negative give the same
answer because it's N squared here so we
can just for practical purposes sum over
only positive N and zero the first term
is just 1 that is not a very interesting
partition function the first time is
just 1 anything you differentiate it
with respect to gives 0 and it simply
says that the
the rotational energy now the rotational
energy is zero okay for very low
temperatures let's find the first and
that's good because well we'll see what
it doesn't admit it
we'll see what does it a minute okay so
in order to get any kind of interesting
answer and to see how the energy
rotational energy does depend on the
temperature we at least have to go to
the next term so the next term is n
equals one plus e to the minus beta H
bar squared over 2i now when beta is
very big
not only when beta is big the two so
there are various situations yeah it
does occur twice thank you that's good
it occurs twice once for positive once
for negative very good okay notice that
there are two distinct wave ways that
this that make that might make this
thing small one way is that the
temperature is very large ah sorry
opposite the temperature very very small
if the temperature is small beta is
large and then this correction here is
very very insignificant but there's
another way even if the temperature is
not so small if I is very small if I is
extremely small it means the coefficient
one over I is very big so that's
tantamount to just saying beta is law is
larger so there are two ways to make
this term insignificant one of them is
low temperature but let's fix the
temperature let's take the temperature
to be fixed and do something different
just shrink the molecule what happens
when you shrink the molecule when you
shrink the molecule this I get smaller
and smaller beta over 2i gets bigger and
bigger and even if the temp
sure is not so low you get driven into
the situation where this function just
drops to zero like a bomb and the
integral is silly you don't do the
integral the good approximation is just
to add a small number of terms each one
getting much much smaller than the
previous what's the next term every term
has a two because the angular momentum
could be positive or negative what's the
next term e to the minus four h-bar
squared over 2i e now e to the minus
theta now this is the fourth power of
this if this is small the fourth power
of it is really really small okay the
next one after that would be the ninth
power of the same thing and so forth and
so on so in a situation where either
beta is large or I is small then we can
safely ignore the higher terms we think
we could also safely ignore this but
since we're trying to find out what the
beta dependence is it's better to keep
it because the first term doesn't have
any beta dependence at all all right so
this is a good approximation for very
low temperatures
what's the logarithm of this remember
this is a very small quantity the
logarithm of one plus a small quantity
is just a small quantity or incidentally
of course if there are n particles we
just raise this to the nth power now so
far this is just the rotational energy
and I'm only concerned with the
rotational energy now the other parts of
it are still there the logarithm of Z is
just going to be twice e to the minus
beta H bar squared over twice I comes in
no sir
yeah twice 2n okay so now we can compute
once we know the logarithm of Z we can
compute the energy stored in rotation we
can compute the energy stored in
rotation all we have to do is
differentiate log Z with respect to beta
so the derivative of log Z with respect
to beta is of course 2 N and then
differentiating with respect to beta
will give us a minus sign it will give
us the same e to the minus beta H bar
squared over 2 on e and then we have to
differentiate what's in here with
respect to beta that will give us H bar
squared over 2i I think I have that
right
let's see differentiate law looks right
that's the derivative of log Z with
respect to beta the negative of it is
the energy stored in rotation and the
energy per particle would just be
divided by n this does not look like the
classical formula a classical formula
was just plain 1 over beta okay this is
one of the beta which meant temperature
the energy stored in rotation was just
temperature this formula has the feature
that when beta is very big when
temperature is low all when I is very
small the contribution is exponentially
small exponentially small this is not so
significant here this
significant factor and the energy stored
in rotation is minut even if we keep the
temperature fixed if we let I shrink to
zero if we shrink to the point particle
limit this simply disappears that's the
solution to the paradox of of molecular
structure and why it is that the
molecular structure degrees of freedom
do not get appreciably excited at least
at low temperatures at high temperatures
they do get excited so an interesting
question is where is the crossover point
between the classical formula and and
this a product now remember this was an
approximation you cannot take this
approximation and study it for high
temperature why not because the high
temperature behavior involves this whole
sum for high temperatures beta is not
small these are not small results and
you've got to add them all up for low
temperature that's the place where you
can just truncate the sum and say only
appreciable contribution comes from the
first term here so you can't mix the
approximations one approximation
high temperatures is to substitute for
sums integrals and that gives you the
classical formula the other
approximation for low temperatures is
just to take one or two contributions
where does this formula go from one
thing to another and I'll tell you where
it happens where is the crossover from
one type of behavior to another it's
when the temperature is such that the
classical energy which would be 1/2 T
1/2 T would be the classical answer when
that is equal or approximately equal to
the energy of the lowest rotational
excitation ok what's the energy of the
lowest
rotational excitation here's the energy
n equals one h-bar squared over 2i e for
temperatures lower than this there just
is not enough energy to excite the atom
into the molecule into rotation this is
not enough energy the temperature is not
high enough to overcome the separation
between energy levels at high
temperature there's no problem you can
excite the rotational degrees of freedom
very easily and it's when the
temperature gets to be such that it
corresponds to one Quantum's worth of
rotation that's about where the
transition from one thing to another
happens so as long as the temperature is
lower than this then rotational degrees
of freedom don't get excited that
depends on the on the moment of inertia
if we wrote the moment of inertia in
terms of the mass and the radius of the
molecule we will find out that when the
radius of the molecule goes to zero in
other words when the when the moment of
inertia gets extremely small the
temperature needed to excite that
rotational degree of freedom gets
infinitely big so that's a resolution
quantum mechanics sort of truncates and
the contribution of very small angular
momentum and you need a certain amount
of temperature before you start to get
the molecule rotating yeah there is a
Boltzmann constant ah my convention is
such that what in textbooks is called K
and I'll use little T to represent the
kV the textbook definition of
temperature then Big T is K times little
T so yes there is a Boltzmann constant
in here and which you would need to put
in if you are actually doing some
numerical work so if you wanted to find
out at what temperature in measured in
unit Celsius or units Kelvin you would
want to put the Boltzmann's constant in
here that evil that would make the
temperature even bigger so okay so let's
see okay okay so it's kind of
interesting to put in some numbers into
here and to find out at what
temperatures do you start to excite the
rotational molecular degrees of freedom
for a molecule with reasonable
parameters is that temperature generally
below the let's a point which is our
lemon arts it's a very high temperature
nor Hiram so the oxygen atoms in this
room it's hard it's hard to imagine that
they're not rotating 0:04 oxygen you
know for oxygen is probably big enough
that that's Yemen or for oxygen I was I
was actually thinking about it I was
thinking about hydrogen and it's
electronic structure hydrogen and
electronic structure it's a rather high
energy for for oxygen I suspect it's
near room temperature I'm not even sure
I'm not sure about at low enough
temperature there is a low enough
temperature where these are frozen out
whether these degrees of freedom are
frozen out or another way of saying it
is that there's a moment of inertia for
fixed temperature which if it's too
small will freeze out these degrees of
freedom yeah yeah yeah I think I think
the temperature for molecular things is
fairly low probably lower than room
temperature for nice large sized
molecules
oh yeah no no they were there and for
hydrocarbon chain yeah I mean you have
zillions of degrees of freedom so it's
nowheres near three-halves or 2 kt it
could be a zillion kt depending on the
number of ways that the molecule can
flap around right okay so that's that's
the basic physics of the diatomic
molecule and why at low temperatures or
very very small molecules you don't have
to worry about the structure yeah louder
yeah absolutely absolutely yeah yeah
certainly it certainly does affect the
specific heat for example just at low
temperatures or small molecule size but
low temperatures the specific heat will
resemble the specific heat of the point
of a molecule system and at higher
temperatures the specific heat me or the
heat capacity will be bigger result
arresting
Ferno temperatures if you add a little
bit of heat not enough to flip the
rotational energy over and that energy
must not have bested in the other in the
translational symmetry that's correct
the words of you I wouldn't yeah what
you say is absolutely right but I would
say if you raise the temperature a
little bit instead of saying you had a
little bit of heat you can imagine
adding a little bit of heat without
changing the temperature one way to do
it would be to add a little bit of heat
but expand the gas so I think the right
language is to say if you raise the
temperature a little bit technically
speaking I wouldn't want to say if you
add a little bit of heat because you can
add a little bit of heat in many ways
including adding heat and expanding the
gas or expanding the volume and then you
wouldn't change the temperature so it's
the temperature which counts here okay
good all right are we are we happy about
the diatomic molecules all right I was
going to talk about magnets a little bit
but I think I think I will turn to
something else and come back to magnets
next time black hole thermodynamics and
this is the kindergarten version of
black hole thermodynamics by
kindergarten version I mean it's based
on and you're not allowed to push me too
hard for precision because the precision
really comes from studying quantum field
theory in the part in the in the
vicinity of a black hole but the ideas
are right and what I'm describing to you
now is very much beckon Stein's
first explanation of why black holes
have entropy and then given that they
have entropy
the various consequences of that and
their applications of things that we've
talked about
but as I said the logic is not going to
be as tight as you might like but
nevertheless it does explain what's
going on pretty well all right let me
just remind you about the important
things about black holes you don't have
to know very much about what a black
hole is what you need to know is that
it's an object which has a mass and a
radius now the radius is now the radius
of the horizon radius and it's the
Schwarzschild radius which I won't
bother denoting R sub s because it's the
only capital R that will be in the
problem and the connection between these
two incidentally a normal gas and so
forth has both an energy and a volume or
if it's if it's a spherical container of
gas it has an energy and it has a radius
and they're independent variables you
can vary both of them simultaneous a
will and it's a two parameter system one
is a control variable the volume the
other is you can also think of it as a
control budget but the other is the
energy the black hole has only one
parameter or at least the simplest kind
of black hole the Schwarzschild black
hole has only one parameter either the
mass or the radius because the mass and
the radius are connected with each other
and they're not independent variables
okay what's the connection between them
the connection between them is that the
radius the radius of the black hole is
equal to twice the mass times Newton's
constant divided I think by C squared
I'm going to keep for the time being I'm
going to keep C
in the formula and because there is this
connection you think of it as a
one-parameter system which is completely
controlled by the energy of it and you
don't have to think about a separate
control parameter which is the size of
the system okay that's this is I think
is the only real thing that we need to
know about black holes we also need to
know that black holes swallow everything
they come in their vicinity and here's
what I want to do I want to add to the
black hole one bit of entropy one bit of
information the minimal amount of
information that I can add to the black
hole in fact what we're going to imagine
is we're going to start with a very
small black hole and we're going to
imagine building up that black hole to a
larger size by throwing in bits of
information one bit at a time now what
is a bit of information mean a bit of
information for us is going to beam
throwing in a particle either there's an
extra particle in the black hole or
there isn't an extra particle in the
black hole so we're going to imagine
throwing in particle by particle and
filling up the black hole until it gets
to a bigger size by adding to its mass
it's very much like filling up a bathtub
full of hot water by adding molecule by
molecule and here's the kind of question
we might ask if we add a certain number
of molecules how high is the level of
the water well that's an easy problem
you know if you know the volume of a
molecule and you add in molecules you
increase the volume of water by n units
and so forth and so on or we know how to
do that problem here now we want to ask
how does the radius of the black hole
grow as you add bits of information okay
so we're going to drop into this black
hole
particles the simplest kind of particle
to throw into the black hole is a photon
why because it's it's the easiest kind
of particle for our purposes so let's
imagine photon by photon we dropped
photons into the black hole but we have
to be careful not to add more than one
bit of information when we throw a
photon into the black hole now supposing
first of all we had a big black hole and
we throw it a photon and that photon was
a well collimated photon from a laser
beam with a short wavelength and the
size of the black hole was a kilometer
well throwing in that one single photon
is a lot more than one bit of
information and the reason is there's
all kinds of information stored in the
location that you threw in the photon in
fact how many bits of information does
it take in order to describe exactly
where you threw in the photon not
exactly but with a certain accuracy oh I
give you a certain accuracy and I say
how many bits of information are there
that are coded or that it takes to code
the location of where the photon goes in
and the answer is well you have a couple
of coordinates an azimuthal and a and
they and the polar angle to describe
you're going to describe those
coordinates to a certain degree of
accuracy which means that a certain
number of binary digits are necessary in
order to specify where you threw in the
photon the number of binary digits is
roughly the number of bits of
information that are stored in the
question or the answer to the question
of where that photon fell through the
horizon so generally so throwing in a
photon like that is much much more than
one bit of information but if I throw in
a long wavelength photon a photon whose
position uncertainty is so large
larger than the whole size of a black
hole then there's no sense if we take a
long wavelength photon whose position is
quantum mechanically as uncertain as the
whole size of the above the black hole
then the only question we can ask is did
the photon get in there or didn't it get
in there is there an extra photon in the
black hole or isn't there so I so it's
not true even though when the photon
enters a black hole gets smeared across
the horizon the photon of course it's
quantum mechanically smeared across a
yes let's go is proton good stay tuned
across surprised and how does our
positional information retained it was
usually smeared across her eyes feel is
it the point is yeah let's come back to
the bathtub full of hot water okay we
drop in a molecule at a certain definite
place inside and on the surface of a hot
water very very quickly for all
practical purposes in particular the
purposes of taking a bath we do not care
where we dropped in that molecule but
information is conserved to the person
to Laplace's master of the universe who
can follow every single particle and so
forth that information is not lost
so when you throw in a single molecule
into the bathtub full of hot water the
entropy goes up by more than one unit
the more the better you know where that
molecule went in the fact that it later
gets distributed throughout the entire
bathtub now or that it gets a
delocalized the information gets
delocalized over the whole bathtub
that's secondary the amount of
information you threw in was whatever it
took to specify where you threw in that
molecule so it's this conservation of
information business or conservation of
microscopic information same thing in a
black hole the
the undecipherable details that are to
microscopic to see on the surface of the
black hole remember the the things which
constitute the entropy remember where
the black where the photon was thrown in
all right so our best strategy then is
to D localize the photon as much as
possible and then there won't be any any
memory of where the photon went in
because there was no sense in which the
photon had a definite location you say
well why not just take an enormous ly
long wavelength photon and the answer is
that wavelengths photons which have a
wavelength now this something I'm going
to just ask you to accept that the
question of whether the black hole is an
absorber or a reflector is dependent on
the wavelength of the radiation that you
throw in if the radiation has short
wavelength by comparison with the with a
short shield radius the black hole is a
complete absorber it will absorb
radiation of shorter wavelength than the
size of the black hole on the other hand
for waves which are longer wavelength
than the size of the black hole II just
get reflected the black hole is almost a
perfect reflector of waves which are
longer wavelength and the size of the
black hole that you have to tell
there's nothing zipper yeah yeah yeah
right he'll Bend it um yeah it'll Bend
it just like a spherical mirror we'll do
whatever a spherical mirror does I don't
know what does a spherical mirror do
reflects and bends and does a variety of
things it'll behave very much like a
mirror so his wound and race or die
from somewheres in that neighborhood
we're not going to keep track of factors
of two so the reflectivity is a
continuous function and it goes from no
reflectivity at short wavelengths to
almost perfect reflectivity and Patrick
perfect reflectivity at very long
wavelengths and the transition region is
in the region of the Schwarzschild
radius and there's a specific formula
that you can work out which I don't
remember and it's not important okay so
the strategy of throwing in the very
very very very long way by the photon
will backfire the photon just won't get
in for sure right on the other hand it's
good enough to throw in a photon whose
wavelength is about equal to the radius
of curvature the the radius of the black
hole it has some chance of getting in
50% chance of getting in for the percent
chance of not getting in I don't know
but since it's delocalized on the scale
of the whole horizon there's no sense to
ask where it fell in and so all there is
then is the question did it get in or
didn't it get in one bit of information
so throwing in a photon of wavelength
lambda equal to the Schwarzschild radius
I said I wouldn't write R sub s but I
wrote it anyway that's the best strategy
for throwing in one bit of information
now next question how much does the
energy of the black hole increase when
you add one bit of information well the
answer is it increases by the energy of
a photon whose wavelength is this big
okay so you have to remember then what
the energy of a photon is in terms of
its wavelength I will remind you the
energy of a photon let's write an e sub
gamma gamma for fault for Photon
the energy of a photon is h bar over
lambda times the speed of light
that's an elementary quantum mechanics
formula Einstein is that Einstein's
formula yeah this is the same as e
equals H nu okay
e equals H bar C over lambda is it H bar
H I think I would take back just H just
H but we're not going to be keeping
track of factors of 2 anyway so my H is
May or 2pi for that matter the
difference between H and H bar is a
factor of 2 pi I'm not really keeping
track of then and then since I'm so used
to writing H bar no you can't do that
illegal but you can set equal equal to
we go equal equal to wiggle all right
strictly speaking this means
approximately equal to proportional to
is better but close enough for our
purposes that's how much the energy
increases so when you throw in one bit
of information the energy of the black
hole increases by this amount okay next
question how much does the radius of the
black hole increase now we have a
formula that tells us the radius in
terms of the mass mass of course is
energy mass is energy so when I apart
from a factor of C squared mass and
energy are the same thing so when I say
that the that the energy of the black
hole increases by this much I'm also
saying that the mass increases by a
related amount
well I'm using a Z equals mc-squared so
what is the change in the mass of the of
the of the black hole you just divide
the change in energy by C squared so the
change in mass when you throw in one bit
is equal to the change in energy H bar C
over lambda oh but now we can replace
first of all we can replace lambda by
our swar chilled lens we'll do that H
bar C over R that's the change that's
the additional energy that you throw in
and now I think we have to divide that
by C squared because of the C squared
here and so the mass of the black hole
changes by this much how how does the
radius of the black and that's a nice
formula throw in one bit of information
that's how much the mass increases okay
how much does the radius of the black
hole increase well we have a formula
relating radius to mass so in principle
we also have a formula relating the
change of radius to the change of mass
all we have to do let's solve this
equation for the mass M M see let's see
let's let's get let's get rid of some of
the miss over here that's
n is equal to C squared R divided by 2 G
do I have that right and twos let's
forget twos tools are not important to
this calculation proportional to we're
trying to make an estimate this is an
issue of making an estimate all right M
is C squared R over G why did I do that
I don't even know why I did that
well it's smarter just to take this
formula as it is and to multiply here's
the change in mass let's multiply it by
twice G over C squared and that will
give us the change in our what I want is
the change in R so let's let's just
multiply by G over C squared the change
in R is G over C squared let's forget
the 2 G over C squared times the change
in mass which is H bar over R times C so
I've now figured out how much the radius
of the horizon changes when I throw in
one bit of information here it is G H
bar small because H bar is small it's
also small because C is large here is
the radius itself so the change in
radius is inverse to the radius itself
the bigger the radius the smaller the
change in the radius when you throw in
one bit but let's multiply the equation
by r that says that r times the change
in R is equal to G H bar over C cubed
one bit of information R times Delta R
is equal to G H bar over
see cube now what is R times Delta R
it's just the change in R squared so
within a factor of two and what is R
squared it's the area of the horizon so
here's what we found out that the change
in the area of the horizon when you
throw in one bit
is a universal constant it does not
depend on the size of the mass of the
black hole the change in area is always
G H bar over C cubed a universal
constant unit of area this has
dimensions of area where every time you
throw in a single bit you increase the
area by the same exact amount all right
so now if we imagine building up the
black hole from a small black hole by
throwing in bits of information at the
end of the process we would discover if
this is if this is the change in the
area when one bit of information is
thrown in how much does the area change
when you're thrown in s s for entropy
when you're thrown in s bits of entropy
just multiply it by s one bit changes
this much as bit to change or then by
now if we build up the black hole from a
small black hole we can just write that
the total area is equal to G H bar over
C cubed times the entropy of the black
hole or we can invert the relationship
and say hey we made a discovery black
holes have entropy equal to C cubed over
H bar G times the area now that's not an
equality that's an a proper that's a
estimated value where was the estimate
well many
any places where our where we made
estimates this is the bekenstein formula
and what it says is that that's how much
hidden information is there in the black
hole it's kind of interesting this is
one of the few places in physics where
h-bar occurs in the denominator
usually quantum effects are small the
existence of an entropy is a kind of
quantum effect but just think about for
a minute what it says is that in the
limit of classical physics the entropy
doesn't go away the entropy becomes
infinite quantum mechanics is not what
gives the black hole entropy quantum
mechanics is what prevents the black
hole entropy from being infinite why
would a black holes have so much entropy
and the answer is very simple you can
hide an enormous amount of information
in a black hole take the Encyclopedia
Britannica and throw it into the black
hole you can't tell the difference
between that and throwing in a few
chickens right you can't tell the
difference at the end so there's a lot
of information potentially storable in a
black hole or a lot of hidden
information that's storable in the black
hole and in classical physics it's not
that there's no hidden information
hidden in a black hole it's that the
potential amount of information is
infinite in a black hole it's quantum
mechanics which keeps it from being
infinite and gives you a finite entropy
all right so that's the origin of
entropy in black hole physics let's talk
about temperature we could do this in
two ways I like one way better than the
other here we have the entropy written
in terms of the area the area can be
written in terms of the radius and the
radius can be written in terms of the
mass and the mass can be written in
terms of the energy so in principle we
have a connection between entropy and
energy when we know the connection
between entropy and energy we can
compute temperature the e equals TDS but
we can short-circuit this we can also
say that the definition of temperature
rewrite the e equals TDS basically this
says that the definition of the
temperature is the change in energy when
you change s by one unit if V s is just
one unit of entropy we can write yellow
approximate Delta e equals T Delta s and
if we change the entropy by one unit
then the temperature is just the change
in the entropy sorry the change in the
energy well let's go back that's what we
started with here is the expression for
the change in energy when we throw in
one bit of information so this then is
the Delta e on the left hand side on the
right hand side Delta s is equal to one
unit of entropy and so this must be the
temperature of the black hole H bar C
divided by its radius we can also write
this and there's a numerical constant
there's a numerical constant or we can
also write this as H bar C divided by
the Schwarzschild radius which is 2 mg
all right the honest answer happens to
be I think 8 pi here but that's not
important to us let's not fool around
with that let's just leave it as M G
that's the temperature a change in
entropy when you add one bit so this is
an application of that idea it's very
interesting and unusual that's unusual
because remember M is the energy of the
black hole and the temperature decreases
with energy so this is a very unusual
situation where a systems energy
sorry we're a systems temperature is
inverse to its energy how many systems
have you ever heard of that
whose temperature increases when the
mass decreases or or when the entity
energy decreases anybody know a system
that does that other than a black hole
okay I'll tell you they're actually
extremely common no no no they're not
that common a stars let's start what
happens to a star when it runs out of
fuel and it radiates and it radiates
away its energy as it radiates away its
energy it shrinks and what happens to
its energy to it what happens to its
temperature temperature goes up as the
SHA as the star runs out of fuel it
heats up it's temperature goes up what
happens is this is let me give you an
example for so just a planet orbiting
the Sun suppose a little bit of friction
a little bit of friction or radiates
away energy in the form of gravitational
waves anything which decreases the
energy of the planet as it goes around
it starts to orbit inward and it loses
its energy by increasing its negative
gravitational energy its energy
increases because gravitational energy
goes up but its gravitational energy is
negative so it spirals in losing its
energy but what happens to the velocity
as it spirals in the answer is it goes
up it loses more potential energy than a
gains kinetic energy by a factor of two
so as it spirals in it loses energy but
it speeds up and because it speeds up if
these were individual molecules falling
into the
into the gravitating object it would
mean that its temperature goes up so
this is an odd situation all right but
it's not all that uncommon that that the
temperature increases as the energy
decreases the smaller the black hole the
higher the temperature the smaller the
energy the higher the temperature okay
the bigger the black hole the lower the
temperature so a black hole of stellar
mass a black hole of mass of one solar
mass has a temperature of something like
about ten to the minus eighth degrees
Kelvin the temperature is inversely
proportional to the mass so a black hole
at the center of the galaxy with a with
a mass a million times bigger or a
billion times bigger would have a
temperature a billion times smaller of
course there are other reasons why black
holes have temperature having nothing
whatever to do with quantum mechanics
and Hawking and bekenstein and all of
that they may have temperature
observational temperature for a totally
different reason namely there may be gas
swirling around them and as the gas
whirls around them it heats and as a
heat that gives off light but eventually
that gas will be absorbed by the black
hole and when the black hole is in an
environment or which is otherwise empty
space it has a temperature and a
temperature is inverse to its mass so
that's the application of some of the
thermodynamic relationships and some of
the ideas of information energy are
entropy temperature and how they fit
together
to in a surprising way in a black hole
now I mean the temperatures seen by an
observer far outside are it's the
temperature seen by somebody far away
from the black hole detecting photons
which are coming out of a black hole and
measuring their energy and asking what
does that correspond to in the way of a
temperature we haven't done anything
about black body radiation yet if
they're far away from the black hole
it's exactly the same as the Sun is the
temperature that we ascribe to the Sun
the same as the temperature that we
would measure if we lower the
thermometer down to near the Sun the
answer is no the temperature that we
ascribe to the Sun is a little bit less
than the temperature that you would
ascribe to the Sun if you lower the
thermometer down and the reason is the
temperature that a thermometer sees is
dependent on the energy of the photons
which are hitting it the energy of a
photon when it climbs up out of the
gravitational field of the Sun the
energy of the photon decreases so the
energy of the photons that we measure
far away from the Sun is a little bit
less than the energy that we might have
ascribed to it if we stood right at the
surface of the Sun when we do the
thermodynamics of the Sun we do it as
observers who are far away from the Sun
that's the appropriate way to do it the
same thing with a black hole we do it
from the point of view of somebody far
from the black hole if we got close to
the black hole and measured the
temperature it would appear higher just
for the same reason that the temperature
at the surface of the Sun is a little
bit higher how do we how do we how do we
detect the fact that the temperature of
the surface of the Sun is a little bit
higher than the temperature that we
actually measure how would we detect it
from yeah from the position of spectral
lines the spectral lines that we see far
away
look a little bit and less energetic
than the spectral lines that we would
expect from from you know chemical
emissions near the surface of the Sun so
this is the correct temperature to
ascribe to somebody observing the Sun
from far away but it would be your Sun
Sun black hole
you're right to say that the each the
maximum amount of energy per body is
what's inside block maximum air box area
the entropy per unit volume religious
area would be basically with inside a
flat ball that's funny
the more most I think is what what this
is telling you the fact that the entropy
is proportional to the area is that at
least when viewed from outside the black
hole doesn't have an interior all it has
is a is a surface and this is closely
connected with the fact that somebody on
the outside dropping things into a black
hole never really sees them cross the
horizon they accumulate in layers near
the horizon as seen from outside so our
observations from outside the black hole
will always say that the amount of stuff
that you could store on the black hole
is stored on the surface of the black
hole and it's closely connected with
this if you take this sensor and plug it
into the body
you get to ride it out luminosity
luminosity let's do it yes you do
not the coefficient numbers are slightly
off but no entropy is the number of bits
the number of states is the exponential
of the number of bits so entropy is
itself a log remember it's the average
value of the logarithm of some
probability distress in true P is a log
sorry the number of bits is itself a log
for example if you have n bits over
impossible to state systems how many
states are there due to the end what's
the entropy it's the log of 2 to the N
in log of 2 to the N is in so if you
don't want to take another log on top of
that
did you see that area for one bit is
equal to planck's I didn't say it but
that's right the area yeah here okay so
here it is C cubed H bar over G and now
we could stick in some numbers um well
the right way to say it is one bit of
information one one bit of information
corresponds to an area let's call it the
area of a bit the area of a bit is H bar
G over C cubed H bar is tiny G is tiny C
is huge this is a very small number 10
to the minus 66 where centimeters and
it's the punk area yeah I should write
it's a it's the definition of the Planck
area the plunk length being just the
square root of this but it's very very
clear that the fundamental quantity is
an area not a length well you say
whenever there's an area there's a
square root of the area but yeah that's
true
but there are many many different shapes
with the same with the same area not all
of them are squares some of them are
rectangles they have the same area
somehow the fundamental quantity is the
area unit not the length unit that's
what really always comes in two
important
no that's just a point that the the the
entropy is exactly all the internal
structure that's being hidden and
obscured by by the fact that it's a
black hole it doesn't the entropy it
does tell us something it tells us it
tells us how many degrees of freedom how
many elementary objects there are on the
surface or but it doesn't tell us what
they are it doesn't tell us right
somebody asked me a specific question
let me answer it they asked me about the
luminosity of the black hole so we have
the temperature the temperature is I'm
going to now simplify the story not
simplified so much but I'm going to set
H bar and C equal to one so the
temperature then in units in which
plunks constant in the speed of light is
equal to 1 is just 1 over m G in fact in
plunk units and units where H bar C and
G are all equal to one those are common
units that call Planck units the
temperature of the black hole is just
one row one over this is one of em all
right now what's the luminosity of an
object of temperature T there's a
formula the stefan-boltzmann form or is
called stefan-boltzmann formula yeah
yeah and the answer is it's proportional
to T to the fourth the T to the fourth
so apart from the numerical constants
which appear the luminosity Lemar the
luminosity sorry it's not 1 over T that
method avoids T to the fourth times the
area okay T to the fourth times the area
the luminosity a Cordell luminosity
means the energy per unit time
it's radiated from the object is
proportional to the area of course it's
proportional Cree area the bigger the
area at a given temperature the more
lumen are the more overall luminosity
you have times the temperature to the
fourth and there's a numerical constant
called the stefan-boltzmann constant
which is made up out of H bar and and
other quantities but this is the basic
important thing now the area is
proportional to the square of the radius
the temperature is proportional to 1
over the radius that means the area is
proportional to 1 over the temp 1 over
the temperature squared right
temperature is like 1 over the radius
and so the area and so the area the
radius squared is like 1 over the
temperature squared and what we find out
is that the luminosity is proportional
to the square or I have something wrong
here yeah yeah the square of the
temperature
I think that's right yeah yeah now on
the other hand the temperature is also
proportional to one over the mass so
this is one over the mass squared a
bigger the mass the less the luminosity
the bigger the mass the less the
luminosity even though the area is much
bigger the temperature is so much
smaller that it's the temperature effect
which wins and the bigger the black hole
or less the luminosity you can use this
to find out how long it takes a black
hole to evaporate all its energy away
this is the rate at which its radiating
energy one over M Squared you can use
that to find out how long it takes for
the black hole to lose all of its energy
as time goes on the mass shrinks as the
mass shrinks it becomes more and more
luminous and so there's a sort of
runaway process as it shrinks as the
mass increases sorry as the mass
decreases as it radiates the mass
decreases the luminosity increases and
so as with time it sheds its energy
faster and faster and finally just
explodes in an explosion of a energetic
particles so it takes a long time
you're saying that the radiation is not
toys yeah keep in mind the temperature
here has an H bar in the numerator when
you see an H bar in the numerator you
say that's a quantum effect that we go
away when H bar is equal to zero
okay the entropy would be infinite but
the temperature which is the thing that
controls the luminosity the temperature
contains the h bar in the numerator okay
if I neglected to say it of course this
luminosity and this blackbody radiation
that's being radiated is Hawking
radiation that is what Hawking radiation
is so so the logic was you start by
throwing in you start building the black
hole bit by bit you'll notice after a
little calculation that every bit you
throw in increases the area by the same
Universal amount it's sort of as if the
the bits were impenetrable things that
just accumulated on the horizon and
blocked each other out so that the area
has to grow to accommodate more bits and
the area grows with the number of bits
you discover that entropy grows with
area all right that tells you that the
entropy goes with mass in a certain way
if you know the relationship between
mass and entropy you can calculate the
temperature the e equals TDS that gives
you a temperature and from the
temperature you can calculate a
luminosity blackbody radiation and the
result is what is called Hawking
radiation
on one hand I think nothing is good for
black hole the other hand we have no it
doesn't come out of the black hole it
comes off the surface of the black hole
it never gets into the black hole from a
point of view of somebody on the outside
but but let's let's not get into the
subtleties of inside from the point of
view of somebody outside the black hole
it takes an infinite amount of time to
cross the horizon that's just another
way of saying for all purposes of
measurements performed from the outside
of the black hole all things that fall
into the black hole do not fall into the
black hole they accumulate on the
surface of the black hole or just above
the surface now so it's right
No so this is the temperature or okay
that's an interesting question that's it
that's an interesting question um the
Sun has a pretty well-defined
temperature you measure it pretty well
but it's not really in thermal
equilibrium with its environment its
environment is cold on the outside and
that's why it radiates away its energy
okay if it was an equilibrium the thing
in equilibrium won't radiate away its
energy it'll gain energy and lose energy
at the same time now there's a very very
peculiar thing both about the Sun any
system whose temperature is inverse to
its energy has negative specific heat
the rate of change of energy with
temperature is negative negative
specific heat is very unstable it's not
impossible
black holes and stars have negative
specific heat or negative heat capacity
the increase in energy makes the
temperature lower but it always means
the system is unstable if you try to put
it let's imagine we had a black hole in
equilibrium with its environment that
would mean that its environment would
have to have the same temperature as the
black hole and that would mean that it
had the Hawking temperature the
environment okay now supposing
accidentally the black hole emitted a
little bit extra energy you know it's
it's it's in equilibrium so energy is
going back and forth between it in the
environment but by fluctuation by
accident
it emits a little extra energy what
happens to it there's a cool normally if
a system emits a little extra energy it
will cool relative to the environment
and then the energy will flow from the
environment back to the cooler object
and so there's a sort of self of what is
it whatever you call it what regulating
a regulating thing regulating mechanism
which when when an object in equilibrium
gives off a fluctuation a little bit too
much energy it cools the object
and the result is heat flows back into
it what happens to the black hole when
it gives off a little bit of extra
energy it's mass decreases it gets
hotter and so it tries to give even more
energy to the environment because it's
now hotter than the environment so
there's a runaway
on the other hand supposing the opposite
happened it absorbed a little bit of
extra energy what would happen to it it
would cool and it will want to suck more
energy out so negative specific heat is
always an unstable situation where and
black holes in that sense are unstable
if you try to put them in equilibrium
with their environment they will they
will lead to runaway situations so they
can never be in thermal equilibrium with
their environment if you take the Delta
for an energy-rich the the each bit of
energy is equal to an increase in the
area then there has to be too bit of
entropy the entropy but is equal to a
bit of area okay
was part of the simplest part about the
appropriate labor right so the longest
possible wavelength that will get them
through the black hole so does that mean
that there's a small as possible black
hole which would be the area the event
horizon be plenty area exactly and that
because Michael with less than one bit
of information of the make no sense the
opposite to take so associating with a
bit of information is a narrative if you
take folded bits of information you know
that people to the cosmic horizon
connection yes yes the number of bits of
information in the universe is equal to
the area of the cosmic horizon 10 to the
120 it is a lot and then a number of
possible configurations of the universe
is exponential of that right now that
entropy the 10 to the 120 is much bigger
than the entropy that you would count by
looking at all the ordinary material in
the universe most of it is store it out
very close to the horizon of the
universe the ordinary bits of entropy in
the form of stars and why what's most of
the entropy in the university no I mean
ordinary ordinary stuff that that's
visible ok you might think that it was
the background radiation because there
are many many more photons and there are
anything else but in fact it's not true
the entropy is dominated by black holes
yeah there's something like about an
entropy of 10 to the ninetieth of that
order of magnitude in photons in the
observable universe but there are enough
black holes at the Centers of galaxies
mostly that there's another factor of 10
to the 10th entropy in black holes so
most of the entropy of the visible
entropy by visible entropy I mean the
entropy and stuff that can be in
principle seen not associated with the
horizon but associated with or more
ordinary stuff is about 10 to the 110 to
100 units of entropy in addition the
horizon has another pin to the the
cosmic horizon has another factor of 10
to the 10th bigger than that 10 to 100
and 20 altogether and that's just from
knowing how big the universe is and then
computing its area so yeah it's kind of
interesting almost for every for every
ordinary bit in the universe there are
10 to the 10th bits stuck on the horizon
of black holes so almost everything in
the universe is black hole horizon any
arguments that exist or may be about the
existence of black holes with the
Centers of galaxies how does a lot of
data be well I mean no no I mean we're
worth we're counting counting the number
of galaxies and assuming that each
galaxy contains a black hole of
approximately somewheres between a
million and a billion mass black hole
that's what you find you'll find that
most of the entropy are ordinary entropy
the entropy of a galaxy is dominated by
the entropy of the like the entropy of
the vicinity other our galaxy those
space around the galaxy before you get
to the next Galaxy it would be dominated
by the blackbody microwave stuff but
even that is overwhelmed by a factor of
10 to the 10th by the black hole at the
center of the galaxy so it's an
interesting fact interesting fact for
cocktail party you can explain it to
your friends okay for more please visit
us at stanford.edu